Hi Guys welcome back.
So now we are going to talk about change control process and how it should be managed in a project.
But before that we need to understand what a change control is.
So basically here the change means that any change which you do to any project deliverables.
It could be Duckman it could be a requirement called anything basically which is part of the project
deliverables.
Now technically this is performed toward the project where you review and approve the changes.
But for practical purpose and change control process kicks in once the document is signed off and just
like let's say a project has started now.
You'll continue or others start reviewing the changes and approving them.
But after initial round of requirement gathering that let's say if it's a waterfall then there will
be a dedicated phase for requirement gathering for a Jain.
There will be Spruance where you will be in on a the product backlog.
So whether you are doing a design or waterfall you will reach a point when the requirements are frozen
they are signed up for that phase for that Sprint and you are not expected to make any changes in that
and this is the baseline version this is called baselining.
When you sign off and sign off is not a one step process again you will have to walk through the entire
document all the requirements in it with all the stakeholders the sponsors they will approve it and
after getting that baseline.
Now if any change is proposed in this document Lets say you get a new requirement now that will go to
the change control process.
Now most of the organization already have some kind of processes lets say if you receive a change control
Well the overall effort is less than 40 hours which is less than a week.
In that case a lot of companies process them you know directly accept and approve them and they start
working on them.
But lets see if it is going to take more than a week then it will go to a different channel or it will
go through funding and the release management where its delivery will be planned separately.
So all of that does change control process.
But again the 40 US example which I took is just an example it could be 10 hours it could be 40 hours
it could be $400.
And so largely depends upon the organization and the bandwidth of that in the kind of work they do.
But most of the companies today will have a change control board CCV.
Now that board usually consist of project managers sponsors important stakeholders and they review these
changes.
They approved these changes and the processes performed throughout the project as I said earlier.
But it largely change the board is involved after the document or the requirements of baseline and a
change control or other change.
The worst is in itself can be a project a mini project.
It may have multiple requirements it could be small it could be a big change are so big that you can't
even Enorme accommodate in the current release and you may have to plan for the new release.
So don't assume that these changes are usually small these changes could be big.
And anybody any stakeholder can propose change if the question is that who can propose a change request
or change control.
Remember that any stakeholder can ask you to make change and change here as I said earlier refers to
the change in the existing requirements documents corde or any other set up in the project.
And yes even a full stakeholder is asking you verbally.
Let's say you are well in the document you are in submitting your stakeholders verbally asking you to
make the change and you are responsible for documenting that.
So if you are a project manager or even a business analyst or anybody else if you receive a change to
any medium you have to document that and every undocumented change request will be reviewed approved
in NASA approved a decision will be taken on that.
So genes control board can also decide to defer the change request because you know it could be any
reason they may not have enough money at that stage and there may not be enough resources or other resources
and they may simply decline saying that it is not correct or it is not important.
So all change requests are not approved and once a change request is approved it will go through its
cycle of in-home cost estimation activities sequence and what milestones will be unlike the schedule
dates for delivery will be finalized.
And you know resource management and all of that project management will happen for that change request
also.
And these other inboards tools and techniques and the output.
So as far as input is concerned we have project management plan where we have the change management
plan configuration management plan is called baseline schedule baseline cost baseline.
So we're going to understand that when I say that it is kind of and baseline all of this will be part
of in part because when we say that the document has been baseline and it means it implies that the
is finalized.
We know that this is the change we are going to do for this project for this phase.
Now if I am going to make any change to this requirement this functionality it will also impact the
current scoup and KIDU cost all of that change management plan basically provide direction for managing
the change control process.
As I mentioned earlier there could be rules of those 40 years and those kind of rules.
So you may have a process and change management plan will simply guide that process and configuration
management and basically guides what all updates will be made in the documents and other processes.
If theres a change request.
So this is required to make sure that we follow standard procedures in the event of a change request
and then we have the project documents again the basis of estimates which you saw earlier for any change.
We are going to estimate that so initially when we estimate a project we have certain set of requirements.
We know the features we are expected to deliver but if we receive a change after that it is going to
impact the basis of estimates.
So this is going to be our input here of course the requirement traceability Texaco untraceable dramatics
is basically a quality feature which is done to create a requirement from all reason to delivery.
So if there is a new requirement it is going to impact the requirement visibility.
So lets say we are talking about a website now.
Initially there was a requirement that this website should have a search feature.
So we created a search bar like you see in Google or YouTube but this requirement never talked about
having additional features we are let's if you type.
When you start typing in that spot we should display I know options the option the options you usually
see in youtube or other websites.
Let me quickly jump into the Google and show you how it appears.
So I will go to Google dot com Now here if I type anything it will give it to the star balloon to display
certain options which are related to what I have entered in the search bar.
See now you can see that it it is displaying this variety of options here cartoon and there these numerous
options.
Point is this is an additional feature or this is something which is which may look small but.
And if you are in technology you know it is then using a technology called GICs.
Now SGX it will require dedicated coding dedicated for testing design of development everything.
This is not a small change.
Initially even we estimated the project dysfunctionality based on X was not estimated because this requirement
was not there.
Now we had a requirement for such.
And we had a requirement traceability for that search requirement.
Now we will update that requirement.
We will upgrade that traceability with this additional information to make sure that this is also tracked
and maintained.
And then of course any change in the project will have risk.
So Risk report will also be part of our input.
So let's go back slide.
And of course we have the perf so he performs support in first.
He says in my mind are two factors and the organizational process assets and for tools and techniques
we have again the usual suspect except when you can see that we have two new options the autocratic
decision making where one individual takes the responsibility for making the decision for the entire
group could be project manager could be sponsor it could be a technical lead and then we have to meet
the criteria or decision analysis.
Basically it's a decision matrix to provide a systematic analytical approach to evaluate the requested
changes according to a set of predefined criteria.
So let's say I was talking about that as Exchange.
So in this case we may have certain rules you know based on the technology and the kind of technology
and then structure it will need things like that.
So every organization every project will have their own predefined rules and they will use that for
our multi criteria or decision analysis.
Other than that we have to do analysis which I had mentioned earlier that it is used to assess the requested
changes and decide which are accepted so as you can see alternatives.
So we are looking at the alternative Sometimes the change may be good or really good but there is a
workaround which is cheaper and we don't have to make any changes for that in that case.
Stakeholders may opt for that workaround which is not so automatic no not so clean but it's cheap and
we don't have to make any changes for that.
So they may go ahead with that same line.
We had the cost benefit analysis so they are going to do with the cost benefit of the change wording
simply refers to the process of voting.
And as the output of this process of perform and degree to change control we will have approved change
first project management plan update and document updates and these other applications of all the changes
or anything you do in change control process will impact all of these.
So largely everything we can see that we have direct and manage Project Vote change quality control
procurement project management plan update's project document upbraids a variety of other stuff like
you know a resources monitor communications plan procurement management monitoring stakeholder engagement
validates Qube devlopment the side of the team plan risk responses conduct procurement control the school
manage team implement risk responses control procurement control schedule control resources monitor
risk identify a stakeholder control cost manage quality control quality manage the stakeholder engagement
so basically variety of things so because as I said earlier a change in itself can be a project.
So and when we talk about product we are dealing with all of these we have to manage the stakeholders.
We have to manage the quality we have to manage the cost scoup quality all of it.
So that's why this integrated change control management will have applications on all of these things.
So that's it for now and the next video.
We will continue with PLO's project trophy's activity.
Thank you.